Good morning today's דף Daf is 66.
שנה טובה Shana Tova as well, or good last day of 5777.
We pick up in the middle of ס״ה עמוד ב׳, Samech Hey
Amud Bet, about 15 lines down, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. And we're
in the middle of the issue of בעל אוב. Ba'al Ov. We
just had a whole important discussion about what constitutes an act. Does
speech constitute an act? Other types of things. And the
גמרא, Gemara, moving your hands or whatever, but speech in particular is
not an act, probably less because you move your lips, but what
the גמרא Gemara said that it's ישנה בקול. Yeshna b'kol. There's not
really about your body movement, or like the other point of the
גמרא Gemara said like which was ישנה בלב. Yeshna b'lev. It's really
about expression of thought. It's really not about the physical movement of
the body. And then that led to interesting questions because there's an
exception.
עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim is an exception. Yelling at the animal to
stop plowing and so on. So those are interesting sort of issues,
but that's like the whole discussion
about what's considered a
מעשה. Ma'aseh. Anyway, now we continue to the issue about the various
acts
of witchcraft, raising the dead, whatever they are, some of which are
actually punishable by the death penalty. The two in which specifically are
the בעל אוב Ba'al Ov and the ידוני. Yidoni. So let's take
a look here. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: בעל אוב אחד המעלה בזכורו,
Ba'al Ov echad hamaleh bezichuro, or בזכרו, bezachro, or whatever.
רש״י Rashi says this means that you cause it to rise up
through somehow, or like the spirit rests on the man's male organ,
on his penis. Although some Soncino wants to say that maybe this
word just means like that it's done through some type of an
incantation. But anyway, ואחד הנשאל בגולגולת, V'echad hanishal b'gugoles, or whether you
do it through like the whole Hamlet scene there, speaking to the
skull and having the spirit speak from the skull. Either way is
considered a בעל אוב. Ba'al Ov. מה בין זה לזה, Ma bein
zeh l'zeh, what's the difference? מעלה בזכורו אינו עולה כדרכו, Ma'aleh b'zichuro
eino oleh k'darko, when you do it this first way,
the dead spirit doesn't come up in the natural way, it rises
up feet first. ואינו עולה בשבת, V'eino oleh b'Shabbos,
and it won't come up on שבת. Shabbos. נשאל בגולגולת, Nishal b'gugoles,
however, if you do it through the skull, עולה כדרכו, oleh k'darko,
then the body raises up, the spirit raises up naturally from the
head first. ועולה בשבת, V'oleh b'Shabbos, and it rises up on שבת.
Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says: עולה? Oleh? What do you mean
rises up? להיכא סליק, L'heicha salik, where's it rising up to? הקמי
מנח, Hakamay manach, it's right in front of you. It's in the
skull, which is a little funny because you would think that it
means like you see a vision of the body rising up. But
maybe the idea is that if you're asking a skull, it's not
seeing a vision of the body rising up, it's just having the
skull speak. So what do you mean that it rises up on
שבת? Shabbos? הקמי מנח, Hakamay manach, the skull's right in front of
you. אלא אימא עונה כדרכו, Ela eima oneh k'darko, it answers naturally.
I don't know what it would mean to answer not naturally, maybe
through its natural voice. ועונה בשבת, V'oneh b'Shabbos, and it answers on
שבת. Shabbos.
Okay, he could do it without having to set it within a
sorcerous joint.
Oh okay, that's true too because yesterday we spoke about it
like resting in the knuckles or in the joints. So maybe here
it's like it's really residing in the skull. Okay, that's an interesting
point way of reading it.
ואף שאלה זו שאל טורנוסרופוס את רבי עקיבא. V'af she'ela zo sha'al
Turnusrufus es Rabbi Akiva. This question טורנוסרופוס Turnusrufus asked רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. אמר לו, Amar lo, he said to him: מה יום מימיים?
Ma yom miyomayim? Why is שבת Shabbos a special day? It's arbitrary,
why did God say why do you guys celebrate שבת, Shabbos, why
not Wednesday?
אמר לו, Amar lo, he said to him: ומה גבר מגוברין? U'ma
gever migovrin? And why are you such an important person? Like why
are you different than any other Joe Schmo on the street?
אמר לו, Amar lo, he said to him: דמרי צבי, D'mari tzevi,
because my master the Caesar has appointed me. That's why I have
my status. אמר לו, Amar lo, so not some intrinsic quality. Of
course, obviously, presumably, you're picked because of some intrinsic quality, but okay.
Anyway, he said back to him: שבת נמי דמרי צבי. Shabbos nami
d'mari tzevi. Okay, שבת Shabbos is different than Wednesday because that's the
day that God picked. Not some inherent in the day necessarily. Of
course, then say historically that was the day that God rested, but
okay. אמר לו: Amar lo: הכי קאמינא לך. Hechi ka'amina lach. No,
no, no, he said, you misunderstood me. That wasn't my question. Here's
my question. מי יימר דאידנא שבתא? Mi yeimar d'idna Shabbasa? Who's to
say that today is שבת? Shabbos? Maybe you guys lost track over
five thousand years. How do you know that what the day you
call שבת Shabbos is actually שבת? Shabbos? Maybe you're off by a
day or two. Maybe it's what the Christians call it, maybe it's
Sunday, maybe it's Friday, who knows what it is, maybe it's Wednesday.
I just threw in Christians for a total anachronism anyway. Okay, it
wasn't so anachronistic, but anyway. אמר לו: Amar lo: דמרי צבי. D'mari
tzevi. Okay. אמר לו, Amar lo, he said to him: נהר סמבטיון
יוכיח. Nehar Sambatyon yochiach. סבטיון, Sabbatyon, I guess, סבטיון. Sabbatyon.
So
this is a mythical river that apparently roars the whole week and
on שבת Shabbos it's silent.
So that's like a heavenly river?
No, it sounded like they believed it was an actual river. I
don't know what to tell you if he's telling טורנוסרופוס. Turnusrufus. סבטון
Sabaton is
שבת, Shabbos, right, exactly. Yeah, but
it's some mythical river. Anyway. Okay now, but now the tie-in to
us is, בעל אוב יוכיח. ba-ov yochiach. We just said that if
a בעל אוב ba-ov tries to raise the dead in a certain
way, it won't come up on שבת. Shabbos. So that shows you
שבת Shabbos is a special day. קברו של אביו יוכיח, Kivro shel
aviv yochiach, and your father's grave is evidence. Why is your father's
grave evidence? שאין מעלה עשן בשבת. She'ein ma'ale ashan b'shabbos. Smoke comes
up from it every day, but not on שבת, Shabbos, because the
idea is that on שבת Shabbos those in גיהנום Gehennom are given
a day off. Even those in גיהנום Gehennom get a day of
rest on שבת Shabbos and they're not, you know, burning in the
fires of גיהנום. Gehennom. So you can see that by the smoke
that doesn't rise from your father's grave. Okay, so he was not
happy with this proof. So, because it obviously suggests that his father
was burning in גיהנום. Gehennom. So אמר ליה, amar lo, he said
to him, בזיתו ביישת וקיללתו. bizito biyashto v'killashto.
You have, you know, degraded and disgraced and whatever, cursed my father
through your proof. Luckily somehow Rabbi Akiva survived the exchange. Anyway, okay,
back to אוב. ov. שואל אוב היינו דורש אל המתים. Shoel ov
haynu doreish el hametim. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, you're
now describing the אוב ov as the guy that sort of is
a necromancer and raises the dead, you know, raises the spirit of
the dead. So that's what the תורה Torah describes as דורש אל
המתים, doreish el hametim, but דורש אל המתים doreish el hametim is
not, you know, seems to be a לאו, lav, not punished by
death. So how is it different? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
דורש אל המתים כדתניא. Doreish lameisim k'detanya. No, no, no. דורש אל
המתים Doreish lameisim is a different point. The דורש אל המתים, doreish
el hametim, which is a simple negative prohibition, זה המרעיב עצמו והולך
ולן בבית הקברות. zeh hamar'iv atzmo v'holeich v'lan b'veit hakevarot. Somebody
that starves himself, fasts for maybe multiple days and goes and sleeps
in a cemetery in order to be able to hear the spirits
of the dead talking. Okay, רש"י Rashi says that the spirit of
the dead should rest on him and that should help him in
terms of doing his like witchcraft. Okay,
כדי שתשרה עליו רוח טומאה. kidei shetishreh alav ruach tumah. The רוח
טומאה ruach tumah should rest on him, which again, according, because there
are other stories that somebody falls asleep in a cemetery, what is
all that noise? You might go, falls asleep in a cemetery and
hears the dead speak, or you know, hears the angels speaking from
behind the heavenly, you know, curtain. But here it says that the
spirit rests on him and רש"י Rashi says helps him do the
witchcraft, but it's not being directly in conversation and in communication with
the dead. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, שורה
עליו רוח shoreh alav ruach ומאמר, v'ma'amar, וכשהיה רבי עקיבא מגיע למקרא
זה. ukhshehayah Rabbi Akiva megi'a lamikra zeh.
When Rabbi Akiva came to this verse, דורש אל המתים, doreish el
hametim, right, and the idea of דורש, doreish, it's like it takes
effort, you know, you starve yourself and so on. So היה בוכה.
hayah bocheh. He would cry. ומה המרעיב עצמו כדי שתשרה עליו רוח
טומאה שורה עליו רוח טומאה. U'ma hamar'iv atzmo kidei shetishreh alav ruach
tumah shoreh alav ruach tumah. Somebody who goes out and does this
effort in order to be that this impure spirit will reside upon
him, he actually succeeds. המרעיב עצמו כדי שתשרה עליו רוח טהרה. Hamar'iv
atzmo kidei shetishreh alav ruach taharah. If somebody were to go through
a similar process in order to have the רוח טהרה ruach taharah
rest on him, that the divine, that I should be inspired with
let's say prophecy or you know, some type of
a divine sense of a connection with the divine, על אחת כמה
וכמה. al achas kamma v'khamma. How much more so should that succeed?
You know, and this by the way suggests this whole idea of
this like asceticism, you know, like being like a monk or whatever,
going and whatever doing these practices in order to connect to the
divine. But it should succeed, says Rabbi Akiva, but it doesn't. אבל
מה אעשה שעונותינו גרמו לנו. Aval ma e'eseh she'avonoteinu garmeu lanu.
Our sins have prevented this from being affect, you know, us from
having this connection with the divine. שנאמר, Shene'emar, the very appropriate pre-ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah message, כי אם עונותיכם היו מבדילים ביניכם לבין אלוהיכם.
ki im avonoteikhem hayu mavdilim beineikhem l'vein eloheikhem. Your sins have caused
a division between you and your God. So were it not for
the sins, this would actually succeed. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא,
Rava, and with that in mind, אי בעי צדיקי, ibo'ei tzaddikei, if
like the righteous people who actually don't have these sins that divide
between them and God, if they wished, they would be so connected
to God and to the divine power, what's the ultimate divine power?
The power to create. Okay, so if they wanted, ברו עלמא. baru
alma. They could create worlds.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, כי עונותיכם היו מבדילים. ki avonoteikhem hayu mavdilim. It's only
because your sins separate. Without that, you'd be so connected to the
divine that you'd have this power to create. רבא, Rava, now in
that spirit, רבא Rava or some say רבה, Rabbah, ברא גברא. bara
gavra. Actually created. Here's the golem. Here's the golem. Forget it, the
first golem. Okay, רש"י Rashi says it's with the help or the
גמרא Gemara is going to sort of say it's with the help
of the ספר יצירה, Sefer Yetzirah, which is a book, you know,
that is ascribed to אדם הראשון Adam Harishon and supposed to have
the powers of creation in terms of knowing how to combine the
letters of the divine name. So he was able to create a
person. שדריה לקמיה דרבי זירא. Shadrei l'kamei d'Rabbi Zeira. He sent him
to Rabbi Zeira. הוה קמשתעי בהדיה. Hava kamishtayei badeh. So Rabbi Zeira
didn't realize who he was. He thought it was just, oh, רבא
Rava sent me this guy to, this תלמיד, talmid, this student or
something. So he started engaging him in a conversation. ולא הוה קמהדר
ליה. V'lo hava kamahader lei. הוה קמשתעי בהדיה, hava kamshtayei behadei, so
Rabbi Zeira didn't realize who he was; he thought it was just,
oh, רבא Raba sent me this guy to be this תלמיד, talmid,
this student or something. So he started engaging him in a conversation.
ולא הוה קמהדר ליה, velo hava kama'ader lei, but the גולם Golem
couldn't respond. The גולם Golem was speechless because the power of speech
is considered to be the
uniquely human characteristic. אונקלוס Onkelos says on the פסוק pasuk in בראשית
Bereishit where it says ויהי האדם לנפש חיה, vayehi Adam l'nefesh chaya,
right? God breathed into the human being like the divine spirit, the
spirit of life, and it says the human being became a living
soul, אונקלוס Onkelos translated it as became a person of
speech, רוח ממללא. ruach memalela. Okay, speech is often considered to be
the uniquely human characteristic. Not intelligence? Well, the question is degree of
intelligence. Whatever, all philosophers had different views. What makes human beings unique?
And then what do you do with it when you find other
animals have speech and other animals are intelligent or whatever? But anyway,
but even if you could create without being God, without God having
created, there cannot be any actual power of speech.
Okay, so what was it?
אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to this גולם, Golem, I'm
using the word גולם Golem anyway, מן חבריא את, min chavraya at,
you're from those magicians, okay, which is חבר חבר, chaver chaver, right,
as like anyway,
הדר לעפרא, hadar l'afra, go back to your dust.
Is that like an indirect critique?
It sounds like an indirect critique if מן חבריא min chavraya here
means... exactly. Well, it wasn't he technically didn't do it through the
magic, he did it through ספר יצירה, Sefer Yetzirah, but yes, it
does seem to be a pretty big critique of that. There's a
whole interesting תשובה teshuvah of the חכם צבי Chacham Tzvi if whether
a person created through a גולם Golem created through the ספר יצירה
Sefer Yetzirah can count to a מנין. minyan. And if you want
to see a contemporary discussion of that issue, there's a great, okay,
this is probably be the only book in this genre, which is
Jewish feminist science fiction. Anyway, there's a book by Marge Piercy called
He, She, It, which is a whole issue about a post-apocalyptic society
creating an android and trying to socialize it, and it tries to
socialize it by telling it stories to a Jewish community stories of
the גולם Golem and the מהר״ל. Maharal. Anyway, and their questions about
like what defines humanity, and anyway, the מהר״ל's Maharal גולם Golem turns
out to be a woman. Anyway, so go ahead and you can
read that story. Okay, so what happened?
Wasn't this like הלכתא דמשיחא hilchata de'meshicha kind of?
Yeah, he was obviously doing it for fun. Anyway,
okay, I think the conclusion was not, he does not count. Anyway,
okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי חנינא ורבי אושעיה
הוו יתבי כל מעלי שבתא, Rabbi Chanina v'Rabbi Oshaya hava yasvi kol
ma'alei shabsa, so Rabbi Chanina and Rabbi Oshaya
every ערב שבת erev Shabbos they would sit ועסקי בספר יצירה, ve'aski
be'Sefer Yetzirah, they would be learning the ספר יצירה, Sefer Yetzirah, ומיברי
להו עיגלא תילתא, umivrei lehu igla taltsa, and what they would make
for כבוד שבת kavod Shabbos is they would make a third calf.
There's always, third calf is seen I guess as the choice. What
does third mean? Does it mean the third of its age? Does
it mean the third born? So רש״י, Rashi, if it's the third
of its age, רש״י Rashi says then they created it at that
stage of its development. But if it's a third born, רש״י Rashi
says they can't create a third born, but they said they created
it so it had the same taste, it was of the same
quality as a third born calf. Anyway, ואכלי ליה, ve'achli lei, and
that's what they had for שבת. Shabbos. Yeah, well they didn't try
to I guess speak to it. Yeah, it seems like that's more
acceptable than a person. You're not trying to actually mimic God to
the same degree, I guess. Okay. תנו רבנן. tenu rabanan. It's also
interesting of course that it's ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, right? Because animals
and humans were created on ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. So talk about
creating, being like God here. This is obviously like very dangerous stuff
side by side of saying how some of this all this stuff
is אסור assur with things looking a lot like this is אסור
assur and some of it is חייב מיתה, chayav mita, we're talking
about how some אמוראים Amora'im did stuff in a היתר hetter way.
You know, very, I don't know. Okay. תנו רבנן. tenu rabanan. מעונן.
me'onein. Now what's a מעונן? me'onein? We're going to the other people
listed that do these types of magic but they're not punishable by
death. One is the מעונן. me'onein.
Yes, today's the ערב, erev, the day before the day of creation.
Oh,
right, that's true. That's a good point, right. And day of creation
is being not the first day of creation, but the creation of
humans. So right, it's very much... okay, very good point. Excellent point,
there you go. תנו רבנן, tenu rabanan, a מעונן, me'onein, what's מעונן?
me'onein? So רבי שמעון אומר זה המעביר שבעה מיני זכר על העין,
Rabbi Shimon omer zeh hamavir shiva minei zachar al ha'ayin, seven types
of, רש״י Rashi says, semen on the עין ayin in order to
give somebody some sort of ability to do witchcraft, the עין ayin
and מעונן. me'onein. וחכמים אומרים זה האוחז את העינים, vechachamim omrim zeh
ochez et ha'einayim, somebody who is basically an illusionist that uses hand
motions to actually make people think that they're doing magic when they're
not, which raises a very important contemporary question: are you allowed to
be a magician? So you know, some say nah, nowadays everybody knows
it's all fake, nobody right, entertainment, nobody really believes it's real. It's
different if you're doing it and somebody believes you're doing magic even
though in fact what you're just doing is an illusion, but if
everybody knows it's an illusion...
so
I'd have to look, but I think it's a pretty widely accepted
that if people know... I guess if you get at a certain
level where it looks so amazing that even though some part of
your brain registers you know, some part of you thinks it's real,
that maybe is a problem. But we should all get to that
מדרגה. madreiga. Okay, anyway. All right, so it says רבי עקיבא אומר
זה המחשב עתים ושעות. Rabbi Akiva omer zeh mechashev itim vesha'ot. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
no,
it's more like... Like the person that does, what are those called,
horoscopes? Like you, from the word עונה. onah. So each of these
are different words. One is עין, ayin, or two versions of עין,
ayin, eyes. Here it's עונה, onah, times, the you know you say
what is a propitious time to do something or a dangerous time
to do something. Meaning astrologically. Astrologically or through signs. Okay, let's take
a look.
ואומר ve'omer היום יפה לצאת hayom yafe latzet today is a good
day. You know, you will be successful in romance today. Right? Like
of the horoscope. Right? למחר יפה ליקח lemachar yafe likach tomorrow is
a good day to do business. לימודי ערבי שביעית חטים יפות limudei
arvei shevi'it chitin yafot people that plant ערב שביעית erev shevi'it the
wheat will turn out good.
So what's wrong with that?
I don't know. It wasn't because it wasn't a farmer's comment. It
was this year, he was saying, whatever.
Meaning not like, you know, רוח צפונית? ruach tzonit?
No, no, no, no, no. It's something about astrological or signs or
some type of, right, not a natural read of the world. Okay.
עקורי קטניות מיאור רעות ikurei kitniyot mi'or ra'ot if you pull out
your legumes,
it'll prevent them from being bad. Again, this is not practical advice.
This is because of this person's ability to, like you know, read
the sign whatever, you know, mystical signs or whatever. תנו רבנן. tanu
rabanan. Okay. Anyway, by the way, I should mention by all of
this, which I haven't mentioned yet, you know, that there's a major
debate of Rambam and Ramban. Rambam says this is all נארישקייט, narishkeit,
none of this ever none of this of course doesn't work, and
the whole reason that the Torah was מחייב mechayev you was when
you do things to make it look like you're doing it, like
as we mentioned the illusionist, Rambam says it's all sort of fake.
It's all illusionary, and the Torah never says it. If that's the
way you present yourself and do as if you're doing this stuff,
raising the dead or whatever, you know, then that's what the Torah
is מחייב mechayev you מיתה. misa. The Ramban, so that's obviously a
rationalist approach, which probably many of us could identify with, but it's
not פשט pshat of the Torah. So you know, so the Ramban
says no, the Ramban says I'm sorry Rambam, I you know, what
what can I tell you? No, according you know, according to the
Torah, this stuff actually does work, you know? We're not supposed to
employ it, but it actually does work. Okay. Anyway, it's the whole
story that we had yesterday of the witch of עין דור, Ein
Dor, right, or whatever, you know, raising whatever by שאול Shaul and
שמואל. Shmuel. So that certainly the פשט pshat of that is that
it was working. Anyway. Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. מנחש, menachesh, what's
a
מנחש? menachesh? זהו אומר פיתו נפלה מפיו מקלו נפלה מידו. zehu omer
pito nafla mipiv maklo nafla miyado. Similar to the idea of this
goes away from like horoscopes to superstitions. Okay. Now you go figure
out why every Jewish grandmother goes and falls into this category, okay?
Yeah, no, but so somebody who said, I don't know what to
tell you, you know, "Oh, the bread fell from this person's mouth,
that's a sign of X, Y, and Z." You know, the stick
fell from this the person dropped the stick, that's a sign of
the something else. בנו קורא לו מאחוריו beno kore lo me'achorav
his son called him from behind, עורב קורא לו orev kore lo
if a raven calls out to you, צבי הפסיקו בדרך tzvi hifsiko
baderech if a deer runs across you in the way, נחש מימינו
nachash miymino if a snake appears to your right, ושועל משמאלו veshual
mismolo or a fox to your left, each one of these is
a sign for something else. Okay? I really do not know how
come superstitions do not fall into the, you know, into this category.
Yeah, anyway. All right. I maybe they do, right? Okay. Anyway. אל
תתחיל בי שחרית. al tatchil bi shacharit. Now that, here's something like
says, this the next thing is actually very interesting. Talking about ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashana, we do סימנים. simanim. By the way, I mean
if I was give I should have give I whatever, if I
was giving a שיעור, shiur, there's a whole major discussion in the
פוסקים: poskim: why can we do the סימנים simanim on ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashana? Why isn't that this problem of like מנחש menachesh and
so on? This should be a sign for something. You know, there's
a difference between whether you're sort of recognizing that you you mean
it as sort of symbolic and aspirational, right? יהי רצון, yehi ratzon,
right? Exactly, as opposed to saying "because this happened," exactly, causative, "this
is predicting that this is going to happen." Okay, but anyway, here's
something that sounds like the type of thing people would say, like
"Oh, you know, it shouldn't be like a bad... don't start off
the day on a bad note, that'll actually mean that bad things
will happen today." So for example, okay. אל תתחיל בי. al tatchil
bi. No, cannot. אל תתחיל בי
שחרית. al tatchil bi shacharit. Rashi says if somebody comes to collect
taxes from you, say, "Don't start don't don't ask me first. Ask
somebody else first. Like I shouldn't..."
No, but like come to me second. Don't come to me first.
Okay? Because then that'll be a סימן רע siman ra that bad
things will happen to me if I'm the one that started it.
Or at some you know, don't do something bad first thing in
the morning. אל תתחיל בי, al tatchil bi,
don't start with me. שחרית, shacharit, it's the first thing in the
day. Come to me later in the day. ראש חודש הוא, Rosh
Chodesh hu, it's ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, it'll be a סימן siman
bad for my whole month. מוצאי
שבת הוא, Motzaei Shabbat hu, it's Saturday night, it'll be if something
bad happens Saturday night, it'll be a bad סימן siman for the
whole week. Okay. All of that seems to be a negative prohibition,
but you know, whatever, go figure out how come people do that.
Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Our Rabbis taught. לא תנחשו ולא תעוננו.
lo tenachashu velo te'onenu. Do not do these things, ניחוש nichush and
עינון, onon, we just discussed what those were. כגון, kegon, here's a
different explanation: אלו המנחשים בחולדה בעופות ובדגים. elu hamenachashim bechulda be'ofot uvedagim.
People that give like like incantations with like cats and birds and
fish. So what does that mean? So if you look at Rashi,
he says weasel. Thank you. Sorry, right, חתול chatul is a cat.
Thank you, weasel. Rashi says מנחשים menachashim כשיוצאין לדרך וכשמתחילין בשום דבר.
kesheyotzin laderech ucheshematchilin beshum davar. So Rashi says it doesn't mean what
we said before like חובר חבר, chover chaver, like you use some
type of an
incantation. One wonders if it also includes the whole looking at entrails,
which was a common thing in the ancient world. Okay, moving on.
המחלל, Hamachalel, I will send it out, okay? It'll probably be an
hour before it's
Mincha. המחלל את
השבת בדבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת. Hamachalel et HaShabbat bedavar shezedono kares
veshigagato chatat. So we are moving on from the aspects of חיוב
סקילה Chiyuv sekilah from things like sexual sins and עבודה זרה-related Avodah
zarah types of things to חילול שבת Chilul Shabbat and cursing parents
and so on. Okay. So, חילול שבת, Chilul Shabbat, which are the
ones that you get סקילה Sekilah for? The types of things that
had you done them without witnesses, you would get כרת, Kares, and
if you did them unintentionally, you would be, you would bring a
חטאת. Chatat. So basically means the מלאכות. Melachot. But what might that
be coming to exclude? So the גמרא Gemara says: מכלל דאיכא מידי
דחילול שבת הוי ואין חייבין עליו שגגתו חטאת וזדונו כרת. Michlal de'ika
midi de'chilul Shabbat havei ve'ein chayavin alav shigagato chatat ve'zedono kares. גמרא
Gemara says from this it sounds like you could have something that's
labeled as חילול שבת Chilul Shabbat that would not fall into this
category of getting stoned and of getting bringing a sin offering. What
is that? Meaning you could sort of say you didn't honor שבת,
Shabbat, you didn't make קידוש, Kiddush, but you wouldn't call that חילול
שבת. Chilul Shabbat. What would you call חילול שבת Chilul Shabbat that
would not be one of the thirty-nine מלאכות Melachot that would not
fall into this category? So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי היא? Mai
hi? What is it? תחומים ואליבא דרבי עקיבא. Techumim ve'aliba de'Rabbi Akiva.
So according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you have the issue of
תחומים, Techumim, אל יצא איש ממקומו ביום השבת. Al yetze ish mimkomo
beyom HaShabbat. You can't go out more than a certain, a certain
distance, like a kilometer outside the city. And for רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that's a biblical issue, not a rabbinic one, but it's not
חילול שבת, Chilul Shabbat, it's, well, it's חילול שבת, Chilul Shabbat, but
it's not a מלאכה. Melachah. You violated a negative prohibition of שבת,
Shabbat, but it's not a מלאכה, Melachah, so it doesn't have all
these weighty punishments. And רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir I'm sorry, skipped a line,
הבערה ואליבא דרבי יוסי. We mentioned this a few days ago, according
to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, since the תורה Torah says לא תבערו
אש בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת, Lo tiva'aru esh bechol moshvoteichem beyom HaShabbat,
that on שבת Shabbat you're prohibited to make a fire, so you
could see that as like the paradigm חילול שבת. Chilul Shabbat. But
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says actually it was singled out to tell
you that it's a negative prohibition and it is חילול שבת, Chilul
Shabbat, but you don't get the death penalty. Okay, so those would
be cases where they're considered violations of שבת, Shabbat, חילול שבת, Chilul
Shabbat, without getting the death penalty. Moving on: המקלל אביו ואמו אינו
חייב עד שיקללם בשם. Hamikalel aviv ve'imo eino chayav ad she'yekalelam ba'shem.
Now we're going to cursing one's parents, but it's only if you
curse them with God's name and with God's explicit name. קללם בכינוי,
Kilelam be'kinui, if you use a
non-explicit name of God, like אל El or אלוהים, Elohim, not יהוה
Yud-Kay-Vav-Kay and so on, and not the way it's spelled. רבי מאיר
מחייב, Rabbi Meir mechayev, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, says you're still חייב.
Chayav. וחכמים פוטרין, Ve'chachamim potrin, the חכמים Chachamim say you're exempt. You
might remember that there was a similar debate by cursing God, whether
you have to use God's explicit name or not. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מאן חכמים? Man chachamim? Who are the
חכמים Chachamim who say that you have to use God's explicit name
for cursing of parents? So רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי היא. Rabbi Menachem
be'Rabbi Yosi hi. It's רבי מנחם Rabbi Menachem the son of רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. דתניא, De'tanya, it was taught in a ברייתא: Baraisa:
רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Menachem be'Rabbi Yosi omer: בנקבו שם
יומת, Be'nokvo shem yumat, when he articulates God's name he shall be
put to death. Okay, that's in the context of
blaspheming. But that's blaspheming God. So מה תלמוד לומר שם? Mah talmud
lomar shem? Why did it just say בנקבו יומת? Be'nokvo yumat? Why
the extra use of the word שם? Shem? So רש"י Rashi uses,
reminds us that earlier the גמרא Gemara used that to teach that
you have to curse God's name with God's name. You have to
use God both as the subject and the object. But here we're
saying that word is extra and it's going to teach us something
not about blasphemy, it's going to teach us something about cursing parents,
about a different type of cursing. Okay, so what does it say,
שם? Shem? So מה תלמוד לומר שם? Mah talmud lomar shem? לימד
על המקלל אביו ואמו שאינו חייב עד שיקללם בשם. Limed al ha'mekalel
aviv ve'imo she'eino chayav ad she'yekalelam ba'shem. So רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי
Rabbi Menachem be'Rabbi Yosi says that teaches you for something else, not
cursing God but cursing parents, that you have to use God's explicit
name. Okay, now we're going to unpack the whole פסוק Pasuk by
parents. It says: איש איש כי יקלל אביו ואמו מות יומת אביו
ואמו קלל דמיו בו. Ish ish ki yekalel aviv ve'imo mot yumat
aviv ve'imo kilel damav bo. A man, any man who curses his
mother or father, you know, he will be put to death. You
know, his mother or father he cursed, his blood is on his
head. So let's unpack that פסוק. Pasuk. איש איש, Ish ish, any
man: לרבות בת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. Lerabbot bat tumtum ve'androgynos. Not just a
man, not just a male, but the double איש איש, Ish ish,
any person, includes a female and people of indeterminate gender or of
mixed gender. Okay. אשר יקלל את אביו ואת אמו, Asher yekalel et
aviv ve'et imo, that curses his father and mother: אין לי אלא
אביו ואמו. Ein li ela aviv ve'imo. So it's reading the ו
Vav as 'and'. Curses both his father and his mother at the
same time. So I only know somebody who curses both his father
and his mother.
אביו שלא אמו אמו שלא אביו מנין? Aviv shelo imo imo shelo
aviv minayin? How do I know even the father without the mother,
the mother without the father? תלמוד לומר אביו ואמו קלל דמיו בו,
Talmud lomar aviv ve'imo kilel damav bo, the end of the פסוק:
Pasuk: His father and mother he cursed, his blood is on his
head. אביו קלל אמו קלל, Aviv kilel imo kilel, either one is
enough. דברי רבי יאשיה, Divrei Rabbi Yoshiyah, that's רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiyah
says. What he's doing here is he is, you know, he's looking,
if you look, פסוק Pasuk says is איש איש, Ish ish, איש
איש, Ish ish, כי יקלל אביו ואמו מות
יומת.
Ki yekalel aviv ve'imo mot
yumat. אביו
ואמו קלל דמיו בו.
aviv ve-imo kilel
damav bo. So what it's saying is here, next word יקלל, yekalel,
it has the word אביו. aviv. And here, next to word קלל,
kilel, it has אמו. imo. So therefore אביו קלל אמו קלל. aviv
kilel imo kilel. So you know to read them not that you
have to do both together, but either one is enough because those
two are juxtaposed, each one is juxtaposed to the word
קלל. kilel. Okay, where were we? Okay, דברי רבי אושעיא. divrei Rabbi
Oshaya. רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonatan omer, Rabbi Yonatan says no. משמע
שם כאחד ומשמע אחד בפני עצמו. mashma shem ke-echad u-mashma echad bifnei
atzmo.
When the Torah says a ו, vav, the ו vav means both
'and' and 'or'. And therefore you should read it in its most
expansive way. Just by saying אביו ואמו קלל, aviv ve-imo kilel, it
means father or mother. We would not read it to mean only
both together. The only time you would read a ו vav to
say it requires both together is עד שיפרוט לך הכתוב יחדיו, ad
she-yafrat lecha hakatuv yachtav, unless it says explicitly together. So for example
Rashi says it says לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדיו, lo tilbash
shatnez tzemer u-fishtim yachtav, don't wear שעטנז shatnez wool and linen together.
Or לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור יחדיו, lo tacharosh beshor u-vachamor yachtav, don't
plow with an ox and a donkey together. So together means both
at the same time. Otherwise it means one or the other. So
you don't need this fancy דרשה derasha you just did. Okay, מות
יומת, mot yumat, now the put to death, בסקילה. biskilah. That's through
stoning and that is the focus of our פרק. perek. אתה אומר
בסקילה או אינו אלא באחת מכל מיתות האמורות בתורה, ata omer biskilah
o eino ela be-achat mikol mitot ha-amurot ba-Torah, you say stoning or
is it another execution, another way of killing? נאמר כאן דמיו בו
ונאמר להלן דמיהם בם, ne-emar kan damav bo ve-ne-emar lehalan dmeihem bam,
the classic link of דמיו, damav, דמיהם, dmeihem, their blood is on
their head. מה להלן בסקילה, ma lehalan biskilah, the same way over
there we learned it was סקילה, skilah, אף כאן בסקילה, af kan
biskilah, here too. עונש שמעתי, onesh shamati, fine, that's the punishment for
cursing a father. אזהרה מנין, azharah minayin, where do you know it's
prohibited? תלמוד לומר אלהים לא תקלל, Talmud lomar Elohim lo tekalel, do
not curse אלהים, Elohim, which could mean God and it could mean
the judges. Either way it doesn't mean father. So how we're going
to get from that to father and mother? We'll see. אם, im,
now first it says like this, well look, father would certainly be
covered in the following cases. אם היה אביו דיין, im hayah aviv
dayan, let's say your father was a judge, הרי הוא בכלל אלהים
לא תקלל, harei hu bikh'lal Elohim lo tekalel, then that's covered by
don't curse a judge. Okay, that's not by virtue of him being
your father. ואם היה אביו נשיא, ve-im hayah aviv nasi, let's say
he was a king, or a, which is how נשיא nasi is
read, or some type of a leader, הרי הוא בכלל ונשיא בעמך
לא תאור, harei hu bikh'lal ve-nasi be-amcha lo ta'or, do not curse
a prince in your nation. Wonderful. That gets a prince or a
judge. ואינו לא דיין ולא נשיא, ve-eino lo dayan ve-lo nasi, let's
say he's not in either of those
categories, מנין, minayin, where do you know that that would be prohibited
to curse the father or mother? אמרת הרי אתה דן בניין אב
משניהם, amarta harei ata dan binyan av mishnehem, you can make a
sort of, you know, a common denominator between the two of them.
לא ראי נשיא כראי דיין ולא ראי דיין כראי נשיא, lo rei
nasi ke-rei dayan ve-lo rei dayan ke-rei nasi, the unique characteristics
of a נשיא nasi are not like those of a judge and
of a judge are not like those of a king. לא ראי
דיין כראי נשיא, lo rei dayan ke-rei nasi, the unique characteristics of
a judge are not like those of a king, שדיין אתה מצווה
על הוראתו, she-dayan ata metzuveh al hora'ato, a דיין dayan is very
weighty, you have to follow their ruling. It says that when you
go
to the judge that will be in that place in the Temple
Mount, you have to listen, you're not allowed to sway to the
right or
to the left. כראי נשיא, ke-rei nasi, that's not like a king
שאי אתה מצווה על הוראתו, she-iy ata metzuveh al hora'ato, you're not,
well you're obligated to follow the edicts of a king, the like
the legislation of a king, but you're not obligated to follow the
legal decisions of a king. Okay, so
therefore that's where a judge is weightier. Okay, so לא ראי נשיא
כראי דיין, lo rei nasi ke-rei dayan, but in the following way
a king is weightier, שנשיא אתה מצווה על המרתו, she-nasi ata metzuveh
al hamrato, a king you are forbidden to rebel against him, meaning
not just to violate his
legal interpretation but to do acts
of rebellion. כראי הדיין שאי אתה מצווה על המרתו, ke-rei hadayan she-iy
ata metzuveh al hamrato, which does not apply to a judge. הצד
השווה שבהם, hatzad hashaveh shebahem, so what's the common denominator? שהם בעמך,
she-hem be-amcha, they're Jews, ואתה מוזהר קללתם, ve-ata muzhar kilatam, and of
course this is going like a very broad common denominator. You would
have said they are in positions of authority, right? But anyway,
ואף אני אביך שבעמך ואתה מוזהר קללתו. ve-af ani avikha she-be-amcha ve-ata
muzhar kilato. So that covers father as well. He's a Jew, he's
in your nation, you can't curse him. Mar says one minute, והלא
הצד השווה שביניהם שאין כן גדולתם גרמה להם. ve-halo hatzad hashaveh she-beineihem
she-ein ken gedulatam garmah lahem. No no no. They have a narrower
common denominator that their status, their high status, is why you're not
allowed to curse them. Okay, that wouldn't necessarily apply to a layperson.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so the verse
teaches לא תקלל חרש, lo tekalel cheresh, do not curse a deaf
person. So that באומללין שבעמך הכתוב מדבר, be-umlalin she-be-amcha hakatuv medaber, there
it's not talking about people of a high status, there it's talking
about unfortunate people, people that would normally be mistreated or marginalized by
society, right? People that you would normally feel you're free to do
what you want with impunity, right? So if you have people that
are on high status of society and people that are often
treated by society in ways that allows people to act with them
with... impunity, you got the whole range of society, so covers everybody,
which is okay.
So, מאי mai one minute גמרא Gemara says מלכי שכני חושך גרמא
לו malki shechenei choshech garma lo maybe it's only prohibited by a
deaf person because that is that because you know because of that
unique status and maybe we have to protect that person because he
could be abused. No, נשיא בעמך יוכיח. Nasi be'amecha yochiach. No, the
other end of the extreme will prove it, like the judge or
the king, that they you know that they don't need protection right
by the law from this, they're in this lofty status and you're
still not allowed. One minute, מה לנשיא בעמך שכן גדולתם גרמא להן.
Ma leNasi be'amecha sheken gedulatan garma lahen. No, but they're because of
a different reason. They're in positions of authority and therefore they have
to be,
you know, you owe them deference and respect. So one person has
to be protected, the others are owed deference and respect. You don't
know it applies to everybody in the middle. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, but if we do a common denominator, the only
common denominator is is that they're in your nation. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
חרש יוכיח. Cheresh yochiach. חרש Cheresh will prove that it's not about
a lofty status. וחזר הדין, ve-chazar ha-din, we go back and forth.
לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה, lo re'i
zeh kire'i zeh velo re'i zeh kire'i zeh, each one's unique characteristics
are not like the other one. הצד השוה שבהן, hatzad hashavah shebahen,
the common denominator with all these three is שבעמך, she-be'amecha, they're in
your nation. Right, the word בעמך be'amecha is based on the פסוק,
Pasuk, it says ונשיא בעמך לא תאור. ve-nasi be'amecha lo ta'or. So
it's picking up on that word בעמך. be'amecha. Anybody in your nation.
ואתה מצווה על קללתו, ve-atah mitzuveh al kilelato, you're forbidden against cursing
them. אף אני אביא אביך שבעמך ואתה מצווה על קללתו. af ani
avi avicha she-be'amecha ve-atah mitzuveh al kilelato. So I will include also
your father that you are forbidden.
No, מה הצד השוה שבהן שכן משונין. mah hatzad hashavah shebahen sheken
meshunin. One minute. What they all share in combination is that they
are unusual, which is funny because, you know, unusual is such a
generic term. But what it basically is a way of doing it's
creating an umbrella term which is saying, you're right, one requires a
prohibition because of their lofty status, the others is a prohibition because
they need to be protected and each one has something unusual about
them and it wouldn't necessarily apply to a person who doesn't have
anything unusual about them. Okay, so even though that's very generic because
the גמרא's Gemara right, like you have both extremes you should be
able to make a common denominator, but nevertheless, maybe not, maybe it's
limited to those cases. Yes.
Does the person have to hear the curse?
No, clearly not because of the case of the חרש. Cheresh. Right.
But also in general.
But that's why you might think you could act with impunity. No,
but the person doesn't have to hear the curse. Person goes ahead
and in his room with two עדים edim curses out his father
or his mother, they haven't heard it, he's חייב מיתה. chayav mitah.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אם כן נכתב קרא. ela
im ken nechtav kra. Okay, fine. You don't want to learn it
from a common denominator, we'll learn it from the fact that there's
an extra case. Because the פסוק Pasuk could have just said two
out of those three. It could have said חרש Cheresh plus one
of the other two, one at one end and one at the
other. It didn't have to have all three. אם כן נכתב קרא
או אלוהים וחרש. im ken nechtav kra o Elohim ve-Cheresh. Either give
the judge and the חרש. Cheresh. או נשיא וחרש. o Nasi ve-Cheresh.
Or the king and the חרש. Cheresh. אלוהים למה לי? Elohim lamah
li? So why did it need the third of those three? אם
אינו עניין לגופו, im eino inyan legufo, you don't need it for
the thing itself because at least there that you would have learned
it from the fact that the others are there that at least
somebody of a similar lofty status would have also been included, right?
Even though you wouldn't necessarily have included everybody in the middle. But
so since one of them is extra, תנהו עניין לאביו. tenahu inyan
le-aviv. So you use it to teach about father that so the
extra one basically teaches you that it applies to everyone, applies to
everyone, the extremes and everybody in the middle. Fine. So that's how
we know that there's a prohibition against father. Of course, by a
normal person you curse it's just a negative prohibition. By the father,
the same prohibition that applies to everybody when it's transgressed with a
person's father or mother is punishable by death. So you understand it's
a little interesting. You're not allowed to curse anybody. It's all within
the same prohibition. But if you violate that for a normal person
it's just a negative violation. If you violate it for your father
or mother, punishable by death. Okay. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this:
הניחא, hani nicha, where am I? Okay. למאן דאמר אלוהים חול. le-man
de-amar Elohim chol. That makes sense if אלוהים Elohim is a secular
word, meaning it means a judge. Then we understand how we could
use it like we just did to cover all people. אלא למאן
דאמר קודש. ela le-man de-amar kodesh. But if it means don't curse
God, if it's the basis for prohibiting blasphemy, blasphemy, so מאי איכא
למימר? mai ika lemeimar? What can you say? דתניא, de-tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא. braita. אלוהים חול דברי רבי ישמעאל. Elohim chol divrei
Rabbi Yishmael. Rabbi ישמעאל Yishmael says אלוהים Elohim in the verse is
a does not mean God, it's secular, it means a judge, and
that's a prohibition to curse a judge. רבי עקיבא אומר אלוהים קודש.
Rabbi Akiva omer Elohim kodesh. No, it means God. Okay. So for
according to Rabbi עקיבא Akiva that it means God and we don't
have a verse about cursing a judge, we only have a verse
about a king
and a חרש, Cheresh, a deaf person, we don't have anything extra
to teach me everybody in the middle. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like
this: ותניא, ve-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braita. רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer, אזהרה למברך את השם מנין?
azharah le-mevarech et hashem minayin? Where is the verse that prohibits cursing
God? תלמוד לומר אלוהים לא תקלל. talmud lomar Elohim lo tekalel. So
that according to Rabbi עקיבא, Akiva, it's from this verse of not
cursing אלוהים, Elohim, God, meaning God, not a judge. So according to
that, how... So how do you learn everybody in the middle? So
the גמרא Gemara says: למאן דאמר Le-ma'an de-amar אלהים Elohim חול, chol,
if אלהים, Elohim, first of all, also the question is if אלהים
Elohim means a judge, where do you learn you're not allowed to
curse God from? It's like either way it's a question. So גמרא
Gemara says fine, we're going to learn both from אלהים. Elohim. It's
not going to be limited to one or the other. למאן דאמר
Le-ma'an de-amar אלהים Elohim חול chol if אלהים Elohim means a judge,
גמר קדש מחול, gamar kodesh mi-chol, we learn out we don't limit
it to meaning judge, we also apply
it to God. Could be based on a קל וחומר, kal va-chomer,
could be that we'll see in a minute, although אין מזהירין מן
הדין ein matzinin min ha-din although we'll see in a minute maybe
we just get it from the phrasing of the verse. That it's
not limited to judge. It also means God. למאן דאמר Le-ma'an de-amar
אלהים Elohim קדש, kodesh, גמינן חול מקדש? gaminin chol mi-kodesh? So so
but if you say that אלהים Elohim is God, can you just
as you're not allowed to curse God can you learn out from
there that you're not allowed to curse a layperson, a judge? בשלמא
Bi-shlama למאן דאמר le-ma'an de-amar אלהים Elohim חול chol גמר קדש מחול,
gomar kodesh mi-chol, it's a little repetitive here. If if it means
a judge, okay fine from a judge you could say if you
can't curse a judge you can't curse
God. אלא Ella למאן דאמר le-ma'an de-amar אלהים Elohim קדש, kodesh, גמר
חול מקדש? gamar chol mi-kodesh? Just 'cause you can't curse God you
can't curse a judge? So it could be so גמרא Gemara says
no.
דילמא הקדש אזהר החול לא אזהר, Dilma ha-kodesh az-har ha-chol lo az-har,
maybe it's only forbidding us against cursing God, not against cursing a
judge and then we also won't have everybody in the middle. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. אם כן לכתוב קרא לא תקל. Im
ken lichtov kra lo sakel. Then why didn't it just say לא
תקל lo sakel with one lamed? Although that might have meant treat
lightly. Anyway not to curse. But anyway this is the דרשה. drasha.
מאי לא תקלל? Mai lo tekallel? What's the purpose of the double
lamed? To tell you שמע מינה תרתי shema mina tarti to tell
you both that the double lamed teaches you that אלהים Elohim means
both meanings, both God and a judge and therefore it's a basis
against cursing God and it's a basis against a judge which is
learned to teach you everybody in the middle including father and mother.
Okay so that is the and so we did one sort of
set which basically was forbidden sexual sins, עבודה זרה avodah zarah related
stuff, שבת, Shabbos, and then and then parents. And now we're going
to do essentially the same type of grouping a second time. So
we go back to sexual related sins. Okay הבא על נערה מאורסה.
Ha-ba al na'arah me-urasah. So before we were dealing with a case
of incest,
relatives, now we're dealing with marriage. Okay a maiden who is betrothed.
And all of those qualities are going to be important and she's
a virgin. Okay so all those qualities are important. Otherwise normal case
of adultery is punishable by חנק, chenek, strangulation, the lightest form. This
is סקילה, sekilah, the weightiest. That's when it is a נערה מאורסה.
na'arah me-urasah. Okay הבא על נערה מאורסה Ha-ba al na'arah me-urasah אינו
חייב, eno chayav, you don't you're not חייב chayav for this particular
category,
regardless it'll be adultery and there'll be a death penalty, but for
this particular category of getting סקילה sekilah you're not חייב chayav עד
שתהא נערה, ad she-tiyeh na'arah, she has to be a נערה na'arah
which means from the age of 12 to about 12 and a
half, בתולה besulah she has to be a virgin, מאורסה me-urasah she
has to be betrothed. Not single and not נשואה, nesuah, not fully
married. Okay והיא בבית אביה ve-hi be-veit aviha and she has to
still be living with her father. So even if she doesn't yet
have had נישואין, nissuin, even if she was basically given over, the
husband sent some they were betrothed, they were going to then do
the חופה chuppah and get married, the husband sent some messengers to
go pick her up from the father's house and bring her to
his house. So even when she's on the way, it doesn't mean
she's out in the store, בית אביה beit aviha is conceptual right?
It's not that this happens in physically the four walls of her
father's house. But once she is conceptually being taken from her father's
house and moved to her husband's house, even if she has not
yet come to her husband's house and they haven't had a חופה
chuppah and they haven't had intercourse or whatever, and even though technically
she's still a נערה מאורסה, na'arah me-urasah, she's only betrothed, but she's
no longer conceptually in her father's house once she's been like picked
up and in the process of going to her groom. Okay and
at that stage it is no longer the סקילה sekilah category. So
in in those
cases without all of those qualities, without all those criteria it would
not be סקילה. sekilah. Similarly
בא עליה שנים, bo al shenayim, let's say two people had intercourse
with her. Now of course you would say well that's obvious because
then she's no longer a virgin by the time of the second
guy. But the case would be let's say it actually was that
the first guy was an act of anal intercourse. So that's a
question of how do you define virginity. Does virginity mean never having
had intercourse? Does it mean that the hymen wasn't ruptured? You know
so here it says in that case הראשון בסקילה והשני בחנק. ha-rishon
bi-skilah ve-ha-sheni be-chenek. Yes that the second one gets strangulation, does not
get stoned because even that type of an act makes her considered
not a virgin. But this is actually debated, it's debated in the
beginning of כתובות, Kesuvos, right? A virgin gets 200 in her כתובה,
kesubah, a non-virgin 100. What about somebody that engaged in anal intercourse,
right? Would that be considered a virgin or not a virgin? What
say the flip? Let's say somebody's hymen was ruptured not through an
act of intercourse. Is that woman a virgin? Right? So anyway so
same this is sort of a question that occurs in many contexts.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תנו
רבנן tanu rabanan: *Tanu Rabbanan*, our Rabbis taught. נערה *Na'arah*, a maiden,
ולא בוגרת *v'lo bogeres*, not a fully mature woman, so not 12
and a half, for that's an age where all of her pubic
hair has come in or okay, not just two pubic hairs. בתולה
betulah. *Besula*, a virgin, ולא בעולה *v'lo be'ulah*, she cannot have had
intercourse. מאורסה *Me'orasah*, she is betrothed, ולא נשואה nesuah, *v'lo nesuah*. And
obviously not a single but also not נשואה *nesuah*, she's hasn't had
חופה *chuppah* yet, hasn't had sex with her husband, hasn't even been
had this act of חופה *chuppah* which which symbolizes she's in her
husband's home. בית אביה *Beis aviha*, in her father's house, פרט לשמסר
אב לשלוחי הבעל *prat l'shemasar av l'shluchei habaal* to exclude cases even
before the חופה *chuppah*, she's given over to the husband's messengers and
she's in the process of being brought to the husband's house. So
conceptually she's no longer under the father's control and no longer in
the father's house. Okay, אמר רב Rav יהודה אמר רב Rav *Amar
Rav Yehudah Amar Rav* says רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* in the name
of רב *Rav*, זו דברי רבי Rabbi מאיר *zu divrei Rabbi Meir*.
These are the words of רבי Rabbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that says
that it has to be exactly a נערה *na'arah*, our משנה mishna.
*mishnah*, אבל חכמים אומרים *aval chachamim omrim*, the חכמים *chachamim* say נערה
מאורסה na'arah me'orasah אפילו קטנה ketanah, במשמע *na'arah me'orasah afilu ktanah b'mashma*.
Yes we agree with all these criteria and we agree that if
she's too old she's not in this category if she's a בוגרת
*bogeres*, but נערה *na'arah* does not exclude a younger one. If she's
under the age of 12, if she's a קטנה *ktanah* and married
off by her father a legally binding marriage, that would also be
included. נערה *Na'arah* means she can't be because the whole point is
that she's not independent, right she's still in her father's house. That's
the way the Rabbis read it conceptually. So if a woman if
a girl gets to be of a certain age or she's you
know married and not just betrothed or whatever, once she's no longer
in her father's house she's not in this category, but a קטנה
*ktanah*, that she would still be in this category. Okay, they say
אפילו קטנה במשמע *afilu ktanah b'mashma*. אמרי ליה רב אחאי מדפתי לרבינא
*Amrei leh Rav Achai mi'Difti leh Ravina* so רב אחאי מדפתי *Rav
Achai mi'Difti* said to רבינא *Ravina*, ממאי דמתניתין רבי מאיר *mimai d'masnisin
Rabbi Meir*? Now he says I get that that's the debate of
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים *chachamim*. By the way, the
reason we how we know this is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and
חכמים *chachamim* is not just a debate about סקילה skilah. *skilah*, it's
also a debate about the you know when the תורה *Torah* gives
the fine for a person who like you know seduces, right, a
נערה בתולה betulah, *na'arah besulah*. So there also is where they debate
like who who is in that category. Okay or somebody that claims
that his wife was a נערה בתולה betulah, *na'arah besulah*, you know,
I'm sorry not that. Okay, one minute,
right right, the fine of 50 שקל *shekel*. Okay fine, when a
person seduces a נערה בתולה *na'arah besulah*. So there we know that
there's exactly this debate of the רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the
חכמים *chachamim* that רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says that only when he
seduces a woman who's a נערה *na'arah*, and the חכמים *chachamim* say
even if she's a קטנה *ktanah*. So does נערה *na'arah* exclude a
younger age? Okay and that's the claim that our משנה *mishnah* is
going like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, that נערה *na'arah* means exactly a
נערה *na'arah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אמרי ליה
רב אחאי מדפתי לרבינא *Amrei leh Rav Achai mi'Difti leh Ravina*, ממאי
דמתניתין רבי מאיר *mimai d'masnisin Rabbi Meir*? He you're right, according to
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* it's only a נערה *na'arah*, not a younger
woman, a girl. But how do you know that's our משנה *mishnah*?
למעוטי קטנה *l'ma'utei ktanah*, how do you know our משנה *mishnah* is
saying that if she's younger she's not in this category? נמי דילמא
רבנן היא למעוטי בוגרת *nami dilma rabanan hi l'ma'utei bogeres*, ותולא *v'sulo*,
maybe our משנה *mishnah* only means to exclude older than a נערה
*na'arah*. Where do you see in the משנה *mishnah* that the משנה
*mishnah* means younger than a נערה *na'arah* is not included? אמר ליה
*Amar leh* he said back to him, האי אינו חייב chayav עד
שתהא נערה בתולה מאורסה na’arah betulah me’orasah, *hai einno chayav ad shetehei
na'arah besulah me'orasah*.
Okay because the language because if it was the רבנן *rabanan* it
would say she's,
the language of the משנה *mishnah* is אינו חייב *einno chayav* right,
the language of the משנה *mishnah* is she's not חייב *chayav* until
she is a נערה *na'arah*. So עד שתהא *ad shetehei* means as
a younger age she is not, until she becomes the word until
means prior to this she wasn't. So עד שתהא *ad shetehei* means
that until this as a קטנה *ktanah* she was not in this
category. And if you wanted to say that קטנה *ktanah* was in
this category what you would say is אינו חייב אלא על נערה
מאורסה na’arah me’orasah, מיבעי ליה *einno chayav ela al na'arah me'orasah miba'ei
leh* right, ותולא *v'sulo* מידי *mi'di*. If you wanted to say she's
you know younger is in this category you would say he would
have to be a נערה *na'arah* in order to be whatever. That
would maybe if you say she would have to be a נערה
*na'arah*, that could allow for the possibility that younger is included. But
if you say she's not חייב *chayav* until she's a נערה *na'arah*,
then that means younger is not included. All right so the word
until means younger than this is not included. ותולא *v'sulo* מידי *mi'di*
it's not worth discussing it anymore, the language of until indicates that
our משנה *mishnah* is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, younger than this is
not included. Fine. בעי מיניה רב יעקב בר אבא בר אדא מרב
*Ba'ei minei Rav Yakov bar Abba bar Adda me'Rav*. So רב יעקב
בר אבא בר אדא *Rav Yakov bar Abba bar Adda* asked the
following question of רב *Rav*: בעל לקטנה מאורסה לרבי מאיר מהו *Baal
l'ktanah me'orasah l'Rabbi Meir mahu*? So let's say she's a נערה מאורסה
na’arah me’orasah *na'arah me'orasah* and
but she's a קטנה *ktanah*. So we know she's not סקילה skilah
*skilah*. Okay so what punishment the and the girl wouldn't get punished,
she's a קטנה *ktanah*. What punishment would the guy get? Okay לגמרי
מיפטר ליה *l'gamrei mi'pater leh* is does the guy get completely off
the hook which is
a Because she's a נערה מאורסה, because she technically falls between the
cracks. Like if she was a נערה קטנה מאורסה. na'arah ketanah me'orasah.
If she was the קטנה, she was a
נשואה, or if she was something else, right, then of course she
would be, get the death penalty, it would be חנק. chenek. But
do we say that because she's in the נערה מאורסה category, but
not old enough, maybe complete, completely gets off? Do we say וגמרי
ממעט ליה, vegamri mima'it leh, or do we say מסקילה ממעט ליה?
miskilah mima'it leh? No, no, no, he just doesn't get stoned, but
he would still be like a normal case of adultery and he
would get the חנק, chenek, he'd be put to death? אמר ליה
מסתברא מסקילה ממעט ליה. Amar leh mistabra miskilah mima'it leh. Okay, that's
a relief. It makes sense to say he just doesn't get סקילה.
skilah. He still would be put to death, it's still an act,
I mean, of raping a minor and a whatever, which isn't the
actual thing of adultery, the adultery but anyway, it's an act of
adultery, okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so
wait a minute, but the verse says ומתו גם שניהם, umaisu gam
sheneihem, עד שיהיו שניהם שוין. ad sheyihyu sheneihem shavin. But it says
when it speaks about an act of a normal case of an
adultery, it says that they'll both be put to death. Doesn't this
require that they both be in the same category? Now רש"י Rashi
says this means an unusual idea which we normally don't say, and
this bothers תוספות, Tosafot, but I'm just going to go with רש"י
Rashi because it's simpler. רש"י Rashi says this means
that maybe a man would never be חייב by having sex with
a woman who is married if she was under age. Because since
she doesn't get punished, maybe he would get off as well. Now
that goes against everything we know. We know, right, we've taught this
before, you know, that it doesn't, if one of them is under
age, it doesn't matter, the other one can still be considered an
act of forbidden intercourse and get punished. But here the גמרא is
asking that, okay? So wait a minute, why should he get סקילה
skilah. if she is total, I mean, excuse me, why should he
still get חנק chenek if she is completely getting, if she's not
being, if it's a category where she's not being punished? Okay, funny
question, normally we accept that, but that's the question being asked here.
So the verse says שתיק רב, shasik rav, רב doesn't have an
answer to that, okay? אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel said מאי
טעמא שתיק רב, mai ta'ama shasik rav, why was רב silent? ונימא
ליה, Venima leh, there are cases, what do you mean, it always
happens that we all punish one of the parties without the other?
ומתו האיש אשר שכב עמה לבדו. Umaisu ha'ish asher shakhav imah livado.
It says when a man rapes a girl who is a married,
who is married, it says she's not put to death and he
is put to death and it says he dies alone, she's not
going to die, it wasn't her fault. Okay? So what's the problem?
We see explicitly that you can execute the guy without executing the
girl. The גמרא says וכתנאי, uk'tana'ei, you know what, this is a
debate of תנאים. tanna'im. ומתו גם שניהם, Umaisu gam sheneihem, they both
will be put to death, עד שיהיו שניהם שוין, ad sheyihyu sheneihem
shavin, דברי רבי יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiyah. רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiyah says
they both have to be the same, they both have to be
adults. Again, I'm reading this the way רש"י Rashi does, תוספות Tosafot
does a different reading. Okay, so yes, if the girl is raped,
she's not going to be punished, but and he will, he'll be
put to death even if she's not, if she was forced. But
if they're both willing, then or whatever, forget if they're both willing,
but both of them have to be adults. And if one of
them is a minor, then the man will not be put to
death according to this. That's a pretty radical position, we've never heard
that before. רבי יונתן אומר Rabbi Yonatan omer no, ומתו האיש אשר
שכב עמה לבדו. umaisu ha'ish asher shakhav imah livado. No, no, no,
from this point about the man alone, you do not need them
both to be adults. Even if one of them is a minor,
you can execute the guy. ואידך האי ומתו גם שניהם מאי דרשי
ביה? Ve'idach hai umaisu gam sheneihem mai darshi bei? So if you
say that you can kill the guy even if the girl's a
minor or vice versa, what do you do with the פסוק pasuk
that says they both die? What's the emphasis on both, which sounds
like it has to be equal?
So אמר רבא Amar Rava למעוטי מעשה חידודים. lema'utei ma'aseh chidudin. This
comes to exclude acts of מעשה חידודים. ma'aseh chidudin. What are acts
of מעשה חידודים? ma'aseh chidudin? So רש"י Rashi say acts of חידודים
chidudin are more like, you know, sexual touch without actually being intercourse.
Why is that excluded from the פסוק pasuk of them together? So
רש"י Rashi says it's excluded from the פסוק pasuk of them together
because there are cases of this which is basically pleasurable for the
man and not for the woman. I mean, there are places where
it's pleasurable for both of them. Anyway, the better read of this
is not מעשה חידודים ma'aseh chidudin but מעשה הורדוס, ma'aseh Hordos, okay,
Herodian, because there was like a legend, maybe it was true, I
don't know, that הורדוס Hordos would actually, would be what's it called,
necrophilia, sleep with women after they were dead. Okay, so therefore that
you understand, it's an act of intercourse, but it's not שניהם, sheneihem,
you only have one of them that's alive. So you don't need
them both to be adults for the person to be put to
death. But you need them both to be alive, okay? And if
one of them is dead, it is not punishable by death. ואידך,
Ve'idach, the other will say back, מעשה חידודים לאו כלום היא, ma'aseh
chidudin lav klum hi, you don't need a verse for that, of
course that's not in the category of forbidden intercourse. Okay, now ואידך
האי לבדו מאי דרשי ביה? ve'idach hai livado mai darshi bei? Now
if you say that you need them both to be adults, what
do you do by the verse that says the man alone? suggests
that not only in the case of rape, suggests in general there
can, you can do cases where you, the man alone is liable?
So what do you do with the word לבדו? levado? מאי דריש
ביה? mai darish be? כדתניא, kidtanya, like we taught in the Beraita:
בא על עשרה בני אדם, ba al asara benei adam, ten men
had intercourse, well, anal intercourse with this woman, with this case of
a נערה מאורסה, and she's still a virgin in the sense that
her hymen has not been ruptured. Okay, כולם בסקילה, kulam biskilah, so
the first position is they all get סקילה. skilah She's technically still
a virgin, right, and therefore they, in a certain sense of the
hymen not being ruptured and they all get סקילה. skilah. רבי אומר
הראשון בסקילה וכולם בחנק. Rabbi omer harishon biskilah vechulam bichenek. No, only
the first guy, everybody else gets strangulation. She's no longer considered a
בתולה. So how does he know that? You could just say that's
his definition of בתולה, never having had intercourse. But here we learn
it from the פסוק pasuk of לבדו. levado. לבדו levado means only
one man will get סקילה skilah. for this woman, not other men.
So only the first, nobody who comes after the first. Okay, so
according to one, we learn from the word לבדו levado that if
it's with a minor, she's off and he gets and he gets
punished חנק, chenek, not סקילה. skilah. According to, according to the other
approach, no, only if she's an adult, which is very strange, we
never say that. We always say that one of them could be
an adult and the other a minor and it could still be
a violation. תוספות Tosafot has a different read of this to make
this not violate our normal rules, but I'm not going to worry
about תוספות Tosafot right now. Okay, but the other thing we learned
from שניהם sheneihem and לבדו, levado, from שניהם sheneihem we learned to
exclude the idea of if the woman is dead, and from לבדו
levado we learn to exclude a case of that only the first
man gets סקילה. skilah, Afterwards she's no longer considered a virgin. Okay,
let's just finish the משנה. תנו רבנן: בת איש כהן כי תחל
לזנות. bat ish kohen ki techel liznot. Okay, a daughter of a
כהן, kohen, now we're dealing with this, which is also a case
of a נערה מאורסה except she gets שריפה. sreifah. רבי אומר תחילה,
Rabbi omer techilah, the first one, כי תחל, ki techel, first. וכן
הוא אומר, vechen hu omer, similar it says, ומית האיש אשר שכב
עמה לבדו. umet ha’ish asher shachav imah levado. That man alone. So
what does that mean? מאי קאמר, mai ka’amar, what's it say? אמר
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע: amar Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua: רבי
כרבי ישמעאל סבירא ליה. Rabbi keRabbi Yishmael sevira leh. רבי holds like
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, דאמר ארוסה יצתה לשריפה ולא נשואה. de’amar arusah
yatzta lishreifah velo nesuah. He says that the daughter of a כהן
kohen that gets שריפה sreifah is exactly parallel to the normal girl
who gets סקילה. skilah It's only the
נערה בתולה מאורסה, it's exactly that same special category. When it occurs
by a ישראל Yisrael it's סקילה, skilah. when it occurs by a
כהן kohen it's שריפה. sreifah. But the fact that it is the
exact same category means that you can learn from one to the
other. Okay, because it's basically, when you're in this special category, it's
either סקילה skilah. or שריפה. sreifah. Now, והכי קאמר, vehachi ka’amar, so
this is what it means: אם תחילת ביאתה בזנות בשריפה. im techilat
bi’atah biznut bishreifah. If it is the first act of intercourse, it
is שריפה. sreifah. The same thing we just said before, the first
act of intercourse is סקילה. skilah. After the first act of intercourse,
she is no longer a בתולה, even if it was anal intercourse,
and therefore it's going to be חנק. chenek. אידך אבתרה בחנק. idach
avatarah bichenek. מאי וכן? mai vechen? So what's the point of the
other פסוק pasuk that was quoted? כי התם, ki hatam, just like
we just said by the normal case of a בת ישראל. bat
Yisrael. מה התם בתחילה ביאה קמשתעי קרא, mah hatam bitchilah bi’ah kamishtayei
kra, we said ומית האיש לבדו umet ha’ish levado means only the
first man gets סקילה. הכא נמי דתחילה ביאה קמשתעי קרא, hacha nami
detchilah bi’ah kamishtayei kra, here too, only the first, only the first
act of intercourse is שריפה. sreifah. Afterwards not. Okay, so that is
basically saying, reminding us that the daughter of a כהן kohen gets
שריפה, sreifah, and that according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, which makes
a lot of sense, it's the exact parallel case to a normal
girl who gets סקילה. And for both of them, it is only
the first time, first act of intercourse. Afterwards, even if it was
anal intercourse, she is no longer a virgin and therefore it is
חנק. chenek. אמר ליה רביבי בר אביי: amar leh Ravibi bar Abaye:
מר לאו הכי אמר, mar lav hachi amar, master didn't interpret it
this way. ומנו, umano, who's the master? רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, what does רב יוסף Rav Yosef say? So
רבי כרבי מאיר סבירא ליה. Rabbi keRabbi Meir sevira leh. רבי really
holds like רבי מאיר, דאמר נשאת לאחד מן הפסולים מיתתה בחנק. de’amar
niset le’achad min hapesulim mitatah bichenek. That one, if this daughter of
a כהן kohen is married to somebody who would invalidate her for,
you know, marrying a כהן kohen like a ממזר mamzer or whatever,
חלל, chalal, etc., then she does no longer get שריפה, sreifah, she
gets חנק. chenek. Okay, so it's not about her being a virgin,
it's about the question of being an ארוסה, arusah, but it's about
whether she has been already defiled. Defiled not through an act of
intercourse, but defiled with a person, a man who she's married to
that makes her invalid to a כהן. kohen. והכי קאמר, vehachi ka’amar,
so this is what it means: אם תחילה אחלתה בזנות כי תחל
לזנות. im techilah achaltah biznut ki techel liznot. If the beginning of
her being desecrated, right, because it says if she defiles herself through
sex, through intercourse, so the word תחל techel is being read both
to mean חילול, chilul, defilement, and beginning. and תחילת. techilat. It's the
first thing that defiles her is this act of intercourse, then בשריפה,
bisreifa, she gets שריפה. sreifa. The ואידך, idach, if she's been already
defiled, not means had intercourse, she doesn't have to be a virgin,
but she's been defiled because her husband makes her invalid for a
כהן. kohen. In that case בחנק, bechenek, she gets חנק. chenek. ומאי
וכן? U’mai ve-chen? Why quote the verse of לבדו, levado, which is
a completely different context? סימנא בעלמא. Simana be-alma. That's not really learning
from it. It's just like a way to remember. Oh, לבדו, levado,
only the first thing. It has to be the first. If it's
after the first. Although not like the first interpretation, which means only
the first act of intercourse, this means it has to be the
first thing that defiles her. And if something else had defiled her,
then she would not be getting שריפה, sreifa, she would be getting
חנק. chenek. Okay. שתהיה שנה טובה. She-tihiye shana tova.